One join that is pretty rare, but one we need to
know about is a self join. A self join is a join
between two columns in the same table. Usually, it
occurs when a table has a hierarchical structure,
such as an employee to a manager or a product
with a parent product. In the BikeRepair database,
I have added an Employees table. In running
a SELECT star (SELECT*) statement, meaning
select everything from this table, we
see that most employees have a manager
with a corresponding EmployeeID. Our goal is to
display the last names of both the employee and
the manager. On closer inspection, two employees
should have Bridges as the manager, and the other
should have Handel as the manager. Let's take a
look at the query that has been built using a self
join. I want to first focus on the line with the
join, as the same table is being joined to itself.
However, each table is being given an alias name,
with e for employees and m for what will represent
managers. Then in the join itself, each employee
manager is matching up with an employee ID. Above
the self join, we see the EmployeeID and LastName
being listed with a column alias of employee,
and the representation of the manager's last
name is listed as manager. I will execute this,
and sure enough, we see that two employees
have Bridges as the manager and two have
Handel as the manager. Before we move on to
the next topic, here is a question for you:
What happened to the employee with no manager? The
answer lies in the join. Because this is an inner
join, only employees with managers will appear.
To get the employee without a manager to display,
what kind of join does this need to be? If you
said left join, you are correct as we want to see
all employees, including those without managers.
I will change the join and execute this statement.
We now see all five employees.